■
本字幕由3e-online3E帝國校訂翻譯制作
僅供學習交流,嚴禁用于商業用途,轉載請注明出處
更多精彩字幕請登錄  bbs.3e-online.com
时间轴/后期 剑齿虎
■
翻译/校对    scrawl
40 years ago at the height of the Cold War,
四十年前，冷战正激烈
these nuclear submarines were locked in battle against the Soviet Navy.
这些核潜艇专门被用于对抗苏联海军的战争
Their crews were bound by a code of silence,
潜艇作战人员受到沉默守则的约束
forbidden to tell their families where they were going or what they were doing.
不允许告诉他们的家人他们去哪儿，做什么
Deep in the oceans, submariners from three navies,
海洋深处，三国的潜艇
British, American and Soviet,
英国、美国和苏联
played cat and mouse on the front line of the Cold War.
在冷战前线玩起了猫和老鼠的游戏
I was obsessed with the Soviets.
我很被苏联人吸引
The whole idea was to go in
他们的整个想法就是全身投入
and put a decisive blow and walk away.
果断一击，潇洒走人
我们一直处在备战状态
很坚苦
The Cold War superpowers pledged to reduce their arsenals of nuclear weapons.
参与冷战的三个强国承诺减少其核武器军械库
But beneath the waves,
然而在暗潮之下
Soviet and Western submarines spied on each other,
苏联和西方的潜艇相互监视
hunted each other down
相互厮杀
and prepared to fight a war with enough firepower to destroy civilisation.
并准备好用足够摧毁世界文明的火力大打一战
In that ship we had more explosive power
在那艘船上我们有足够的爆炸力
than all the weapons dropped in World War Two.
比二战中所有投放的武器的爆炸力都强
And we're talking about both sides now.
更不用说双方的力量加起来了
This was a secret war
那是一场秘密的战争
driven by espionage to maintain the tactical advantage.
由间谍活动驱使着来维持战略优势
Can you tell how many propellers it has? Yes.
你能说出它有多少螺旋桨吗？ 能
Can you tell how many blades are on each propeller? Yes.
你能说出每个螺旋桨上有多少刀片吗？ 能
Does one of them have a nick in it? Yes.
其中哪一片上有划痕吗？有
For over 40 years the details of this Cold War stand-off
四十多年来，冷战平衡的细节
have been a closely guarded secret.
一直是保守得很好的秘密
We're in a submarine that actually could sink him in three minutes.
我们所在的潜艇实际上能在三分钟内沉没
He would have difficulty sinking us.
他没那么容易使我们沉没
Now the story can be told.
现在这个故事可以被人所知了
寂静之战
知 己 知 彼
Captain speaking.
船长有话
We shall be going from Plymouth
我们将从普利茅斯出发，
towards the nearest point in the ice edge, north of Iceland.
去冰缘线离这里最近的冰岛南部
The submarines of the 1950s had hardly changed
20世纪50年代的潜艇几乎都是那个样子
since the days of the Second World War.
一直到二战都没有什么变化
But Soviet, American and British sailors didn't mind.
但是苏联、美国和英国的水手们并不介意
Joining up felt like a special calling.
参军像是一种特殊的集结
It's a club, it's a small club,
那是一个俱乐部，小俱乐部
and it's great to be a member of it.
能成为其中一员感觉很棒
?No other love?
♪别无他爱♪
I can probably tell you fairly rapidly
我可以很快告诉你
whether a chap is a submariner after ten minutes of conversation or not.
一个人是不是潜艇人员，只需要和他聊几分钟
# Now that I've known...
♪因为我知道♪
我喜爱海
你站在那里看着船只
划破行过水面
每片海都由自己的颜色
每一次都是不一样的
# Every time, every time...
♪每一次，每一次♪
He said, "Honey, I really don't want to leave you
他说：“亲爱的，我真的不想离开你
but it's just something I have to do.
但我不得不走
I want you to know I don't want to go."
我想让你知道我不想走”
I say, "OK."  He gets upstairs, he's packing and I hear...
我说：“好的。”他上楼，整理行李，我听到
He's happy as a clam!
他非常快活
# ..to glory in your kiss...
♪因你的吻而得意♪
Good company. And good pay.
他人很风趣 是个好伙伴
And we had extra food, special food, called submarine comforts.
我们有大量的特殊食物，叫做潜艇安慰品
Things like tinned sausages, that was a luxury in those days.
像罐装香肠之类的东西在那时候是种奢侈
Still had rationing in this country.
国内还实行定量配给，
And fruit juice. Absolutely amazing.
但我们还有果汁，简直不可思议
Good life.
生活很好
On the surface, submarines were still powered by diesel engines.
在水面上，潜艇还是由柴油机发动
Under water, rechargeable batteries took over.
在水下就用充电电池代替
The maximum sort of speed underwater was sort of 15 or 16 knots
水下最大速度大约是15或16海里每小时
and you could do that for about ten minutes, the battery ran out.
之后最多十分钟电池就耗完了
Oxygen was limited
氧气很有限
so the submarine could stay submerged for no more than 20 hours.
因此潜艇在水下不能待超过20小时
Water was rationed.
淡水也有限
The captain used to say, "I will use the basin,"
船长当时常常说：“我要用洗脸盆”
which is about so wide and about so deep,
脸盆差不多这么宽这么深
"first in the morning and have my shave
“第一个用，然后我要刮胡子
and you make such use of what I leave in the pan afterwards."
然后你们也这么用我剩下的混水”
So that was it.
就是这样
So you would wash in his shaving  foam?
所以你会用他的剃须泡沫洗脸？
So we didn't wash.
因此我们就都没有洗
Echo classified submarine.
回音可以将潜艇分类
Submarine, surfacing on the fourth quarter, sir.
长官，有潜艇，在第四象限位置
The diesel submarine's limitations
柴油机潜艇的局限
meant they were often reduced to acting as training targets
在于它们常常被大材小用当成训练用的目标物
for sonar operators on Nato ships.
提供给北约船只的声呐操作员
Submarine altering course towards us.
潜艇正朝我们这边转向
It was known as "ping running".
这被称作“撞击奔跑”
Ping running is when the submarine runs for a surface ship
撞击奔跑是指当潜艇朝一艘水面船只追赶
who pings on him with his active sonar
该船只用其主动式声呐“撞击”潜艇
and it was a very basic, boring way of spending the time.
这是一种非常基本且无聊的度过时间的方式
We were really acting very much as the loyal opposition in those days
当时我们真的像是忠实的反对派
and without a particularly warlike role.
没有一个特别的战争角色
From sturding to Captain Deezer,
迪泽船长你好
thank you for the Royal Salute,
感谢你的皇家礼炮
and regret we must consider ourselves sunk.
很遗憾我们必须考虑自己被击沉了
In the Cold War stand-off between East and West
在东西方的冷战平衡中
the battle for supremacy was taking place on land,
争夺霸权的战斗是发生在陆地上
not on the high seas.
而不是公海上
In 1956, the Soviet Union invaded Hungary.
1956年苏联入侵匈牙利
For the West, this was an ominous sign
对西方来说，这是一个征兆
that the Soviet still had ambitions beyond the Iron Curtain.
说明苏联仍然对铁幕之外的世界有野心
Well, it's easy to forget now what the Cold War was like.
人们很容易忘记冷战时候的状况
I mean, we lived with a threat from the Soviet Union
我是说，我们当时生存受到了来自苏联的威胁
right up until the fall of the Berlin Wall.
一直到柏林墙倒下为止
Nato's conventional forces were far outnumbered by the Red Army.
北约的常规部队比红军少得多
The West saw America's long-range nuclear weapons
西方把美国的远距离核武器
as an essential deterrent to Soviet aggression.
当作对苏联进攻的主要震慑
You have to go back and think about how attractive nuclear weapons,
你得回过头想想核武器有多么诱人
if you could maintain an advantage,
你能够保持一个优势
how attractive that prospect was for a NATO alliance
这对北约联盟来说是多么有吸引力的前景
that perceived that it could never defend Western Europe conventionally.
北约本以为以传统方式不可能抵挡得住西欧
Anything that could give you the promise of compensating for that,
只要有任何能弥补不足的可能性
and that would preserve basically the status quo,
并且能够维持当时的平衡状况
was incredibly attractive.
任何那样的东西都有无比的吸引力
But in 1957 the Soviets launched Sputnik.
但是在1957年苏联发射了人造卫星斯普特尼克
If they could send a satellite into space
加入他们能发射卫星
they would soon be able to launch nuclear ballistic missiles
那么很快他们就能发射核弹道导弹
against mainland America.
用于对付美国本土
"As Sputnik whirled around the globe,
“正当斯普特尼克绕着地球旋转时
American citizen bases became as vulnerable to Soviet threat
美国民军基地很容易受到苏联的威胁
as Soviet defences had been in the past to the nuclear strike power of America."
因为苏联的防御工事已经超过了美国核打击能力”
It gets the American people alarmed
这是美国人民很惊恐，
that a foreign country, especially an enemy country, can do this.
一个别的国家，尤其是敌国，可以做到这点
I think it's a very bad thing to have around.
我觉得这是一件令人时刻觉得糟糕的事情
- To have these satellites going round?  - That's right.
- 因为这些卫星时刻围绕着？  - 对
As Sputnik went up
随着斯普特可的升空
the Russians were launching missiles more successfully
俄罗斯人发射导弹也更成功了
than the US was at the time.
比当时的美国更成功
We fear this.
我们很害怕
We fear that they have something out there that the majority don't know about.
我们害怕他们拥有一些大多数人不知道的东西
Western Europe could no longer rely on America's land-based nuclear missiles.
西欧无法继续依赖美国的地面基地核导弹
President Eisenhower looked to the navy for a new way to defend the West.
艾森豪威尔总统转向海军以求寻找防御的新方法
President Eisenhower said he wanted to be able to shoot a ballistic missile from sea.
艾森豪威尔总统说他希望能够从海上攻击弹道导弹
We had no missile, we had no warhead,
我们没有导弹也没有弹头
we had no guidance system, we had no submarine.
没有制导系统和潜艇
The US Navy launched a massive programme
美国海军开展了一个巨大项目
to build a new kind of submarine, capable of launching nuclear missiles.
建设一种新型潜艇，能够发射核导弹
# You keep saying you got something for me
♪你不停说你有东西要给我♪
This is a simplified schematic drawing of a nuclear propulsion plan.
这是一幅简化了的原理图，解释核动力推进计划
The part of the navy that Eisenhower liked was the part that had nuclear in it.
关于海军，艾森豪威尔喜欢的就是其中的核
And so this was where the money was, this is what the future was,
因此这就是资金集中的地方，也是未来的寄居地
this is what the West's strategy was at the time.
这就是当时西方的战略
# These boots are made for walking
♪靴子是用来走路的♪
# And that's just what they'll do
♪那就是它们会做的事情♪
# One of these days these boots are gonna walk all over you
♪总有一天那些鞋子会从你身上踩着踏过去♪
Submariners were back in business.
潜艇人员又开始忙碌了
What are we going to do on Thanksgiving?
感恩节我们都做什么呢？
We're going to work, that's what we're going to do!
我们得工作，那就是我们要做的
Your family just almost ceased to exist, you know.
你的家庭好像都不存在了，你知道吗
But we got through it.
但是我们熬了过来
# These boots are made for walking
♪靴子是用来走路的♪
# And that's just what they'll do
♪那就是它们会做的事情♪
We were the pioneers for the finest weapon system on earth.
我们是地球上最精良武器系统的先驱
The nuclear reactor gave the submarine limitless power.
核反应堆给了潜艇无限能源
Twice the speed of a diesel submarine,
速度比柴油潜艇高了一倍
it could also produce its own water and oxygen supplies.
它能够自己产生淡水和氧气供给
As long as there was enough food it never had to surface.
只要有足够食物，核潜艇永远不需要浮上水面
Going from diesel to nuclear was
从柴油机过渡到核能
like going from riding a bicycle to driving a Formula One.
就像从骑自行车变到驾驶一级方程式赛车
Armed with Polaris nuclear warheads,
配备着北极星核弹头
the missile submarine was capable of destroying Soviet cities
导弹潜艇能够摧毁苏联城市
at a range of more than 2000 miles.
范围是2000英里多
In that ship we had more explosive power
那艘船上我们有大量爆炸性能量
than all the weapons dropped in World War Two.
比二战中投放的所有武器都有威力
And we're talking about both sides now.
更不用说双方的力量相加了
It's a terrible responsibility.
那是一份可怕的责任
The modern submariner. A new breed.
现代潜艇，一个新品种
Young, technically oriented.
年轻，以技术为根本
Make your depth 200 feet. Make your depth 200 feet.
将你的深度设置在200英尺...
Hidden in the ocean, impervious to Soviet attack,
深藏在海洋中，不受苏联攻击影响
submarine crews were now on the front line of the Cold War.
潜艇人员如今处在了冷战前线
I said, "This sounds dangerous to me,"
我说：“这听起来挺危险”
and he said, "I am far safer than you will ever be staying at home."
他说：“我在这儿比你待在家里还安全”
He said, "I don't know what's going to happen to you,
他说：“我不确定你会发生什么
and I don't know what's going to happen to this country,
我也不确定这个国家会发生什么
but nothing's going to touch me. I'm...
但什么也不会影戏我，我在
Where I am they can't get me."
一个他们抓不住我的地方”
The defence of the Western world
西方世界的防卫系统
was now in the hands of a small band of young American submariners.
现在由一小撮年轻美国潜艇士兵掌握
It was a tremendous deterrent
这是巨大的威慑力
that was always available to the National Command Authority.
美国国家最高指挥部掌握着它的使用
We felt proud about that and I think the country did also.
我们很骄傲，我相信整个国家都是
The Soviet Union was racing to produce its own missile submarine programme
苏联也正加速生产其自主导弹潜艇项目
but it was beset with engineering problems.
但受到了工程问题困扰
The Soviet Premier Nikita Khrushchev
苏联总理尼基塔赫鲁晓夫
needed a land-based launch site within range of the United States.
需要一个在美国射程以内的地面基地发射点
In the late summer of 1962,
1962年晚夏
Khrushchev sent as many as 40 ballistic missiles to Cuba.
赫鲁晓夫足足输送了40架弹道导弹去古巴
And provoked the worst crisis of the Cold War.
这激起了冷战最严重的危机
It shall be the policy of this nation
应该制定国家政策
to regard any nuclear missile launched from Cuba
将任何从古巴发射的核导弹
against any nation in the western hemisphere
即攻击西半球任何国家的核弹
as an attack by the Soviet Union on the United States.
都看作是苏联对美国的攻击
Four diesel submarines, known as Foxtrots,
四艘柴油潜艇，代号为狐步
were sent to defend the Soviet forces in Cuba.
被派出以保护苏联在古巴的军力
Each was armed with a nuclear-tip torpedo.
每艘都备有核弹头鱼雷
Enough firepower to destroy the American fleet.
火力足够摧毁美国舰队
在三种情况下
我们可以遵从指示使用鱼雷
一，如果你遭到轰炸
并且船体被炸出了洞
二，如果他们在水面上轰炸或射击你
三，如果你得到莫斯科方面的指令
我们的参谋长拉索卡很冷静地补充说
“一旦有需要就使用鱼类，其他的我们事后再来解决”
Anatolii Andreev was a young submariner
阿那托里安德烈夫是四艘潜艇中
on one of the four Soviet submarines.
一艘上的一位年轻潜艇手
最亲爱的索菲亚，我写这封信给你
尽管不知怎样以及何时能寄予你
我真想在你身边
即使只是在我的脑海里
日子并不容易，而且将会更艰难
我不能和妻子通信
但我有个习惯，每月11日
给她写封信
我们驶入了大西洋
我们完全没料到自己发现了什么
As the Soviet Foxtrots neared Cuba,
当苏联狐步潜艇靠近古巴时
the American fleet was lying in wait.
美国舰队静静等候
We knew they were coming.
我们知道他们来了
We had known for weeks because of our detection capabilities,
四星期前我们就知道了，根据我们的探测能力
including our sound surveillance system
包括声音监控系统
which was top secret at the time.
该系统在当时是高级机密
Unknown to the Soviets,
苏联毫不知情
the Americans had placed a 3000 mile transatlantic cable
美国设置了一条3000英里的跨大西洋电缆
deep on to the ocean bed.
深藏海底
It was known as SOSUS.
该电缆被称作声纳监听系统
Devised after the Second World War,
它是在二战后发明的
SOSUS was an early warning system for any approaching enemy Navy.
是针对靠近的敌方海军的预防警示系统
Fixed on the cable was an array of highly sensitive sonars.
电缆上固定有一系列高敏度声呐
As the four Soviet Foxtrot submarines entered the Atlantic,
当四艘苏联狐步潜艇进入大西洋
SOSUS could detect the sound of the submarines
声纳监测系统就能探测到潜艇的声音
and pinpoint their position.
并指出它们所在位置
The Soviet submarines were forced to stay underwater
苏联潜艇不得不呆在水底
with no way of replenishing their dwindling air supplies.
没有办法再补充他们不断减少的空中补给
感觉就像在地狱
空气闷热
没地方扔垃圾，都发臭了
人们在臭气中喘息
闻着粪便和腐食
Our orders were simply to harass them to bring them to the surface
我们收到的命令就是骚扰他们，让他们浮上水面
and we were very, very good at that.
而我们非常非常擅长这一点
索菲亚
我可以从潜望镜看到美国舰队
他们可真大胆
捕杀非常激烈
我们的每艘潜艇都来面对他们的所有舰队
They knew we were right on top of them.
他们知道我们就在他们上头
Our sonar could be used as an offensive weapon essentially.
我们的声呐基本上可以被用作是进攻性武器
We could turn up the volume
我们可以增强音量
and the amplitude of the sound that we could transmit
我们能够传播的声音的振幅十分巨大
and bounce off the hull of a submarine was immense.
声音是从潜艇船体上反弹回来的
爆炸开始了，有时距离非常近
以至于灯泡都炸裂了
光线没有了
Starved of oxygen and overwhelmed by two days of constant pounding,
两天缺氧，被不断的撞击而不知所措
the Soviet submarines were finally forced to surface.
苏联潜艇最终被迫浮上水面
When I jumped out with our flag
当我举着旗帜跳出来时
我站在那里非常紧张
只穿着破碎的内裤——我没有更多的衣物了
身上很脏，没有刮脸
他们会开枪吗
会撞击我们吗
他们会对我们做什么
They didn't really stand a chance. We had them outnumbered.
他们真的没有任何机会，我们数量上远胜于他们
Our skill levels were extremely high,
我们的技术水平相当高
and I felt sorry for them in a sense.
某种程度上我为他们感到遗憾
I welcome Chairman Khrushchev's decision dismantling offensive weapons,
我很高兴看到赫鲁晓夫主席废除进攻性武器的决定
returning them to the Soviet Union under UN verification.
将这些武器带回苏联，由联合国核查
Vladimir Chernavin was a young submariner during the Cuban Crisis.
弗拉基米尔谢尔那文是古巴危机期间一名年轻潜艇员
He would later become commander-in-chief
后来他成为总指挥
of the Soviet Navy.
带领苏联海军
让我来拿吧，你自己来吗
我自己来
他们不得不浮上水面
举起海军旗帜
尽管他们做的是正确的事情
还展现了英雄主义精神
但我们还是败了
他们逼迫我们浮上水面，暴露自己
假如这是一场战争的话，他们早就摧毁我们了
The Foxtrot crews would find no heroes' welcome on their return home.
狐步潜艇人员归国时没有人对他们进行英雄式欢迎
哈，那事情就完全不同了
他们见了我们说
你们浮上水面，还不如不回来更好
参谋长见了我们
我们被指示去清理船只
交还核鱼雷
不仅如此，甚至连仪式都没有
Determined never to be humiliated again,
决心再不能被羞辱
the Soviet leadership instructed their shipyards
苏联领导层吩咐他们的造船厂
to build a new class of nuclear submarine
建造新等级的核潜艇
that could retaliate in the event of an American nuclear attack.
使其能够对美国可能的核攻击进行报复
The whole idea was in some sense driven by Soviet vulnerability.
这整个想法在某种程度上是由于苏联的脆弱性导致的
We're in this very dangerous competition,
我们处在这种危险的竞争中
we're at a great disadvantage,
处于很大的劣势
we really have to achieve parity with the US Navy that have been,
我们真的不得不争取和美国对等
you know, for ten years outbuilding us and had these advantages.
你知道，美国10年来一直比我们建造的更好，拥有这些优势
We have to catch up.
我们必须要赶上
In just five years the Soviet Union built 34 nuclear-powered missile submarines.
仅仅用了五年苏联就建造了34架核动力导弹潜艇
They called the new class Project 667-A.
他们把这种新等级叫做项目667-A
Western submariners dubbed the submarine the Yankee.
西方潜艇人员称其为洋基
我知道那是他们军队的一个部分
最有前途的部分
那就是为什么我想要在潜艇上的生活
要想成为潜艇指挥官
首先必须是共产党员
那是很明确的意识形态
我们知道我们的社会主义是最好的
美国想要组织我们建设社会主义
我确信，有一天当我醒来时
他们会告诉我“社会主义建成啦”
The theory of nuclear deterrence between the superpowers
在超级大国之间核威慑的理论
was known as Mutually Assured Destruction.
被叫做相互确定的破坏力
Many people preferred the acronym MAD.
许多人喜欢其首字母缩写简称MAD
# This is the story of the land of the free
♪这就是自由土地上的故事♪
# And what we have done for your security
?以及我们为了你们的安全所做的事?
# For the greatest thing you must agree
♪因为你无法否认，最重要的♪
# Is that you be safe in the land of the free
♪就是你在自由土地上安全无忧♪
# Safe as can be
♪尽可能地安全♪
The Soviets could go after our bomber bases,
苏联人可以攻击我们的轰炸机基地
they could go after our bombers,
他们可以攻击我们的轰炸机
they could go after our land-based missiles.
可以攻击我们的地面基地导弹
# So then we showed that we had the means
♪因此我们证明了我们有办法♪
# To launch our missiles from submarines
♪从潜艇上发射导弹♪
# We sent the subs far across the sea
♪我们将潜艇远送出海♪
# For retaliatory capability
♪因为有受到报复的可能♪
But they couldn't go after the submarines.
但是他们不能够攻击潜艇
# But then they got the same sort of thing
♪但他们有类似的东西♪
我们从没想过我们会先出击
原本只是在有必要时准备实施报复——假如美国或北约先攻击我们
# With all that power would any state
♪拥有那样的力量，有哪一个国家♪
# Dare to tempt such a horrible fate
♪敢尝试那样一个可怕的命运♪
# Balance of terror
♪恐惧的平衡♪
The nuclear submarine was the ideal weapon
核潜艇是理想的武器
to apply the calculated logic of Cold War strategy.
可以运用冷战策略的合适逻辑
When the ballistic missile submarine came along
当配上弹道导弹潜艇
it was like this perfect match
那真是绝佳组合
between these theories about trying to seek a kind of balance.
尤其是和其他为了寻求平衡的理论相比
You can see unfolding a period of not instability but complete stability.
你将能看到一段时期，没有动乱，完全稳定
We wanted to make sure we could properly deter action
我们想确保自己能正确地制止军事行动
that would be bad for the world, not just for our country.
行动的后果将损害整个世界，不仅仅是我们国家
In 1966 the Royal Navy joined the nuclear club
1966年英国皇家海军加入了核俱乐部（有核国家）
when it launched the first of four ballistic missile submarines.
当时英国率先研发出四艘弹道导弹潜艇
Britain's submarine force would now work alongside the United States
之后英国的潜艇力量与美国相合作
to deter the Soviet Union.
来遏制苏联
The British and American submarine service relationship was extremely close.
英美两国潜艇军队关系非常亲密
We talked about almost everything, and we shared information,
我们几乎无话不谈，相互分享信息
and we had something to offer.
我们相互帮助
Britain's bases in western Scotland
英国在苏格兰西部的基地
would now harbour US and British submarines
如今停靠着英美两国的潜艇
before they headed into the Atlantic.
随后它们驶进了大西洋
Right. Pipe action stations, set condition 1SQ.
对，管道进入战斗位置，设定置1状态
Polaris missiles had a range of 2500 miles.
北极星导弹射程有2500英里
Submarines could hide far from the Soviet Union and still remain a threat.
潜艇可以躲苏联很远并仍然造成威胁
Launcher prepared.
发射器准备
They would be a continuous presence.
他们能保持存在
Ready to launch, 365 days a year.
一年365天岁时准备发射
If you consider the Doomsday scenario,
如果你想象一下末日的场景
which is that the UK has been taken out by a nuclear strike,
也就是英国通过核打击带来的场景
there are instructions on board which tell you what you are then supposed to do.
船上有指令说明告诉你到时候该做什么
Navigation ready.
导航就绪
The envelope was kept in a safe in my cabin behind my bunk.
信封放在我的船舱里床铺后方一个保险箱里
So I slept alongside it
我就和它一起睡觉
and all the other material in that safe every time I lay down.
还包括其他在箱内的材料，每当我躺下我都和它们在一起
It came from the Cabinet office.
信封是来自内阁的
I think it gave instructions about
我想里面的指令是关于
whether you were to fire your missiles and if so what targets.
你是否该发射导弹，以及目标是什么
Well, I must have sorted it out in my mind at some stage
嗯，我在某个阶段想必是在脑中想了一遍
and talked to Toby about it
然后就去和托比谈了
and if he's happy with what he's doing that's OK.
如果他对所做的事满意，那就没问题了
I didn't dwell on it because how can you?
我没怎么细想，我怎么能细想呢
The potential targets for British, American and Soviet missile submarines
英美苏导弹潜艇的潜在目标
were always a closely guarded secret.
一直是保守得很好的秘密
指挥官一直都不知道
那些导弹本来要攻击哪些城市
他的任务就是发射所有的16颗导弹，加起来有160颗原子弹的威力
发射完就结束任务了
Patrols were classified.
巡逻队被分了类
Few were allowed to know the submarine's location.
没有多少人能知道潜艇的所在
Hopefully the navigator knew where you were.
希望导航器会知道你在哪里
But the nearest thing you got was you knew the seawater temperature.
但基本上你能知道的只有海水温度
That gave you the nearest indication
那是你能知道的最多提示了
of am I in the Tropics or am I in the Arctic or what.
能够知道我在热带或北极或其他什么
Critical to the success of the deterrent
对威慑成功很关键的是
was the submarine's ability to remain undetected by the enemy.
潜艇保持不被敌方发现的能力
The prime reason for remaining undetected
保持不被发现的主要原因
was because you wanted to be sure as you went into missile launch mode,
是因为你要确定当你进入导弹发射模式时
that a Soviet submarine that might have been trailing you
一艘可能一直在跟踪你的苏联潜艇
wouldn't then fire a torpedo and take you out.
不会发射鱼雷轰你出局
Staying hidden meant remaining quiet.
保持隐蔽意味着保持安静
Crews were rigorously trained in what was called "noise hygiene".
船员经过严酷训练，课程叫做噪音卫生学
Submariners, it's drummed into them from the first day to the last
潜艇人员从第一天到最后一天都被反复灌输着
that by dropping a spanner at the wrong moment you're capable of getting yourself sunk.
只要在错误的时间掉落一个错误的扳手都能让你被击沉
If a spanner hits a metal deck,
如果扳手撞响了金属甲板
the noise will be transmitted through the hull of a submarine into the ocean.
噪音将被传播，通过潜艇船体进入大海
Sound travels easily through water
声音在水下传播很容易
and enemy sonar would pick up the sound of the spanner.
地方的声呐就会接收到扳手的声音
Britain and America rubber-insulated their decks
英美两国将他们的甲板用橡胶绝缘
to ensure no sound was transmitted outside the submarine.
以确保没有声音传出艇外
Machinery connected to the hull was suspended on rubber mounts.
连接船体的机械用橡胶垫架悬挂
New recruits quickly learned the difference between sounds
新员工很快学会分辨不同的声音
that could be transmitted into the ocean
一种是能够传入海中的
and the ambient noise of voices that stayed inside the submarine.
另一种是由留在艇内的声音发出的环绕噪音
My first day at sea, I always remember this.
我永远会记得我第一天出海
It was a Sunday and, er, there was a church service on board.
那是一个星期天，船上有礼拜仪式
But somebody mentioned to me they give you a free drink so I went down to it.
但是有人对我说他们给我准备了免费酒水，于是我就下去
And then after it had finished, after we'd been singing these hymns, which were quite loud,
等一切结束，唱完响亮的国歌
I went from 1 Deck down to 2 Deck on a ladder
我从甲板1下了梯子到甲板2
and stumbled at the bottom and fell and I made a bit of noise
在下面绊倒了，摔了下来，发出了声响
and the first lieutenant shouted at me, "You're making a lot of noise there."
第一中尉冲我喊：“你弄出了很大的噪音”
And I thought, that's funny because we'd just been singing for the last hour, you know.
我想这真是有趣，刚才一小时前我们还在唱歌
I used to do a lot of chess myself
我以前很喜欢下象棋
and the winner would win a packet of cigarettes.
赢的人能得到一包香烟
# Hold on honey I'd like to say
♪等等，亲爱的，我想说♪
# I'm busting out and breaking away
♪我正在成长，挣脱♪
On a boat, you're on a tin can, underwater for months on end,
在船上，你就像在罐头里，在水下一直待上几个月
and it becomes very close knit.
大家变得紧密结合
# Think about how it's gonna be
♪想想以后会怎样♪
我们船长喜欢拉手风琴
你一定会想“哦天呐”
当他拉的时候，我们都坐在那儿，从中学了各种曲子
我们还进行了一场演出
The only way you identified the days that were going by
确定流逝时间日期的唯一方法
was you got grapefruit segments on Sunday,
就是在周日你可以拿到葡萄柚瓣
you got mushrooms on Wednesday.
周三你拿到蘑菇
Food was critical. We had steak once a week.
食物非常关键，我们每周吃一次牛排
We would have things like lobster once a week.
还有龙虾一类的东西
我们有很多肉类
潜艇上有一些东西
你在店铺里买不到的
We had frogs' legs way too often.
我们有很多青蛙腿
他们把我们喂得很好，都吃不完
我把他们给我的巧克力都收了起来，寄给我在圣彼得堡的妹妹
This time I shall not fail!
这一次我不会输
Oh ye gods, help me!
噢上帝祝我一臂之力
Crews stayed submerged for two months.
人员在水下待了两个月
曾经我做了个梦
梦里有个我认识的医生
塔提亚纳——她很可爱
我梦见她是我们潜艇上的医生
梦那么真实，我醒来后
去那个医生那里敲门
直到门打开
我看到这个大胡子医生而不是美丽的塔提亚纳
我才意识到自己疯了
# Get out of my space
♪离开我的地盘♪
# Leaving now
♪正在离开♪
# I'm leaving now
♪我正在离开♪
The nuclear stalemate between the Soviet Union and the West
苏联和西方的核僵局
failed to deter Soviet aggression in Europe.
没能阻止苏联对欧洲的进攻
I was duty minister in the summer of 1968
1968年夏天我担任责任部长
with the forecast from Nato
北约传来预测
that there would be no invasion in the immediate future,
短期内不会有进攻
and was woken up in the early morning
我一大早被叫醒
to be told that they had invaded with Russian tanks into Czechoslovakia.
被告知俄罗斯开着坦克进了捷克斯洛伐克
"Heavy tanks rolled through the streets of Prague
重型坦克碾压过了布拉格的街道
as Russian, Polish and Hungarian troops
俄罗斯，波兰和匈牙利军队
carry out their cold-blooded occupation of Czechoslovakia."
对捷克斯洛伐克开展了冷血的侵占
We had an enemy and a serious enemy
我们有敌人，很棘手的敌人
and we were in ideological conflict
我们处在意识形态的冲突中
with the Soviet Communism all through the Cold War.
和苏联共产主义有冲突，一直延续了整个冷战
By 1970 the rapidly expanding Soviet fleet
至1970，苏联快速扩张舰队
had further fuelled Western insecurity.
这加剧了西方动荡
I couldn't think why they were building so many ships and submarines
我想不出为什么他们建造那么多船只和潜艇
unless they wanted to use them offensively one day
他们只可能是为了将来有一天要用来进攻
so it didn't seem like a defensive force.
因此这不像是防御型军力
At Northwood military headquarters in north London,
在伦敦北部的诺斯伍德军事总部
naval intelligence devised a new strategy
海军情报机关设计出一种新战略
to locate and follow all Soviet missile submarines.
用以定位跟踪所有苏联导弹潜艇
If war broke out,
如果战争爆发
the West would sink the submarines before they could launch their warheads.
西方将在苏联能发射弹头之前将其潜艇击沉
An organisation was set up known as Task Force 311.
一个名为任务力量311的组织成立了
I was the operations officer for two years
我担任了两年行动事务员
and I ran many, many operations
我组织了很多很多次行动
out of Northwood prosecuting Soviet submarines.
从诺斯伍德攻击苏联潜艇
SOSUS, the Americans' secret underwater surveillance system,
美国水下监控秘密系统  声纳监听系统
remained critical to Western strategy.
对于西方战略依旧很关键
Naval intelligence knew
海军情报机关知道
that with a missile range of just 1300 miles
装载着射程仅为1300英里的导弹
the Soviet Yankee submarines had to cross the Atlantic
苏联洋基潜艇就要横跨大西洋
before they could threaten American cities.
而后会对美国城市造成威胁
As they entered the Atlantic,
正当他们进入大西洋
they still had no idea that SOSUS had located them.
他们仍然不知道声纳监听系统已经定位到了他们
And SOSUS had improved.
该系统还进行了改善
It was now so sensitive
如今十分灵敏
it could differentiate between the frequencies emitted by each submarine.
能够对每艘潜艇的声音频率进行区分
If naval intelligence
如果海军情报机关
could identify the frequencies SOSUS detected,
能识别声纳监听系统探测到的不同频率
they would always know what type of Soviet submarine was entering the Atlantic.
他们就能知道 进入大西洋的是什么型号的苏联潜艇
That became the job of both American and British nuclear submarines in the Cold War,
这就成为了英美核潜艇在冷战期间的任务
which is to acquire those signatures from Soviet submarines
就是获取苏联潜艇的特征
so that they could be put into a database that would be maintained and updated.
以便将之存入数据库，并进行维持和更新
That would enable SOSUS to maximise its effectiveness.
这会促进声纳监听系统有效性最大化
To record a Soviet submarine's acoustic signature
记录一艘苏联潜艇的声音特征
meant shadowing it at close quarters.
意味着要紧紧尾随其后
A new kind of submarine was needed.
这就需要一种新型潜艇
The hunter killer.
猎人杀手
They were weapons of war. They're dark,
他们是战争的武器，他们是阴暗的
they're black. They're aggressive.
是黑色的，有进攻性的
They look evil,
他们看起来很邪恶
and the whole idea was to go in
其核心理念是直接进入
and put a decisive blow and walk away.
致命一击，潇洒走人
The hunter killer was smaller and stealthier than the missile submarine.
猎人杀手比导弹潜艇小且更隐秘
It was also nuclear powered so could stay submerged indefinitely,
它使用核能，因此一直可以保持在水下
shadowing enemy ships.
尾随着敌船
It was a complete revolution.
这是彻底的革命
The whole concept of operations now allowed you to get in close enough
行动的整个理念如今能让你尾随得足够近
to get a good readout from this signature,
能够非常好地采集潜艇特征
which you recognised as only emanating
据此你能够完美的识别出某种声音特征
from the particular sort of target that you were looking for
就是从你想找的那种型号目标上发射来的
so it was almost possible to fingerprint each submarine.
因此几乎可以对每艘潜艇进行声音指纹采集
In 1975
1975年
Britain and America released their hunter killers into the Atlantic.
英美将他们的猎人杀手放入了大西洋
"We're going north," that was the phrase.
“我们在往北”，那是我们的习语
We're going to make a northern run.
我们要向北方前行
When? In the fall.
什么时候？秋天
OK. Make your plans now.
好，现在就制定计划吧
I used to say a quiet prayer and hope that it all went well.
我过去常常轻轻祈祷一句，希望一切都好
A large number of the operations were extremely highly classified.
大量行动是高度机密的
The intelligence they collected was always known as "the take".
它们收集到的情报被叫做“收入”
The whole boat was in quiet mode.
整艘船都处在安静模式
Everybody on the vessel was told to walk around in their stockinged feet, you know.
每个船上的人都被告知要脱了鞋只穿袜子走路
No stomping about. If you didn't have to move, don't.
别跺脚，如果可以尽量别动
Stay in bed.
呆在床上
It was all about trying to get close to them.
一切都是为了接近他们
It was a whispered excitement.
这是在窃窃私语中的兴奋
SOSUS could guide the hunter killer into the area of the ocean
声纳监听系统能够将猎人杀手引导到
where the enemy had been detected.
监测到敌方的那片海域
Then the sonar crews had to identify the submarine's noise signature.
之后声呐人员就需要辨认该潜艇的声音特征
Bearing node 116.
方位点116
Sitting at the sonar stack with the headphones on,
坐在声呐堆栈边上，带着耳机
scanning the water back and forth
来回观测水域
and if you get to a part that sounds different than the rest of it
如果你发现一部分的声音和其他不同
that could be a submarine.
那可能就是一艘潜艇
Bearing node 113.
方位点113
Very quiet, not really so much as a tone,
非常小声，几乎不能算是音调
just sort of a ssssshhhh, a different sound in the water.
只是某种“嘶”声，在水里听起来和别的声音不同
Can you tell how many propellers it has? Yes.
你能说出它有多少螺旋桨吗？ 能
Can you tell how many blades are on each propeller? Yes.
你能说出每个螺旋桨上有多少刀片吗？ 能
Does one of them have a nick in it? Yes.
其中哪一片上有划痕吗？有
We have phase one audible on track 296. Possible dangerous contact.
音轨296上可以听第一阶段，那是可能的危险接触
That is what you listen for.
那是你要听到的东西
You can tell the difference by the rhythmic beats
你能通过有节奏的振动分辨区别
and on the rhythmic beats is one stronger than the rest.
其中一个振动比其他的都强
If one's stronger than the rest
如果某一个比其他的振动都强
there's some sort of damage to that particular blade of the propeller.
那说明那个螺旋桨刀片受损了
There really wasn't a lot of sound to hear,
实际上几乎没有什么声音
it was more like low hums.
更像是低沉的哼哼
Bearing 111.
方位点111
But very quietly.
但是很小声
Once they had found the submarine,
一旦他们发现潜艇
the hunter killer closed in on its prey.
猎人杀手紧跟上它的猎物
我们清楚地知道美国人
拥有的潜艇比我们更隐蔽
并且监测范围是我们的两倍
我听不见它
但我不得不假设它就在我附近
So you'd get in behind the Soviet submarine
所以你就跟在苏联潜艇后面
recording all the radiated noises from the submarine,
记录下它传播出来的所有声音
then usually one of the sonar riders would come out and say,
通常这时一个声呐操控员就会出来说
"No, no, we didn't get enough, we need more."
“不不，我们还获取得不够，我们需要更多”
Sometimes the captain would say, "We'll make another run at it."
有时候船长会说“我们再来一次”
Sometimes he'd say a bad word and say, "You've got enough."
有时候他就骂一句脏话然后说“已经够了”
You weren't fighting the submarine,
你并不在对抗潜艇
you were fighting the bloke who was driving it,
你是在对抗那个驾驶它的家伙
and therefore you had to focus on what these people were like.
因此你需要关注那些人是什么样的
It's all about trying to outwit your opponent.
一切都是为了以机智胜过你的对手
And that game of chess, if you want to call it that,
象棋游戏，或许你愿意这么叫它
to me was fascinating.
它对我来说很有吸引力
Closing, increasing.
靠近，增加
American and British submariners knew
英美潜艇人员知道，
that their ability to go undetected at close quarters
他们有能力在很近的距离尾随而不被发现
gave them the tactical advantage over the Soviets.
这种能力使他们在战术上有优势
Although our numbers theoretically were lower than theirs,
尽管我们的数量理论上说比他们少
in fact, it certainly convinced me
但实际上我完全信服
that we were in a position to win a shooting war
我们处在一个能够打赢热战的地位
against the Soviet submarine service, yes.
可以打败苏联潜艇军力，是的
Collecting intelligence on Soviet submarines wasn't without risks.
搜集苏联潜艇情报是有风险的
We were very conscious that what we were doing was somewhat dangerous.
我们都很清楚我们做的事情有些危险
Frank Turvey was a young engineering officer on a British hunter killer submarine.
弗兰克特维是当时一艘英国猎人杀手的年轻工程员
Its crew of 98 had been at sea for five weeks.
船上的98人已经在海上过了五周
One night when I went on watch,
一个晚上我正值班
I left my sleeping area, my bunk space,
我离开睡觉的地方，我的床铺
and I had to walk through the control room.
我穿过控制室
Everything looked good
一切看起来都很好
and we were in silent mode.
我们处在安静模式
About 25 minutes past midnight
午夜过了25分钟左右，
there was an awful bang.
传来一声可怕的巨响
And crushing and scraping.
伴随着破碎和刮擦声
And we were pushed right over in our chair...chairs,
我们坐在椅子上被推滑出去
about 74 degrees, so we were almost on our backs.
船体倾斜了大约74度，因此我们几乎背面朝下
There were alarms on all of the panels, bells ringing, red lights flashing.
所有控制盘上警报都响起来了,闪着红光
The submarine had lost much of its electrical power.
潜艇几乎断电
The severe listing had also damaged some of its engineering equipment.
严重的倾斜也导致一些工程设备损毁
But a strange thing happened to me.
但有件奇怪的事情在我身上发生了
When I was at school we had a great Latin teacher.
当我上学时,我们有一位优秀的拉丁语老师
One of the sentences he diagnosed in detail.
他详细分析过一个句子
Una salus victus nonum sparare salutem.
（拉丁语）
The one hope of the defeated
被打败的人要想获得希望
is not to think about your safety.
就不要考虑自己的安全
Do the right thing.
做正确的事情
For the next three hours
接下来三个小时
Turvey and his team of engineers fought to stabilise the submarine.
特维和他的工程师队员奋力稳定潜艇
Only later did he ask what had happened.
之后他才问发生了什么
We were told as far as I remember that we collided with ice.
据我的记忆,我们被告知我们撞上了冰
An iceberg.
一座冰山
And, er, that was it.
就是这样了
What did you think when you were lying in your bunk?
当你躺在床上时你想了些什么
I suppose I thought that I was, and all of us, we were lucky.
我大概想着，我和所有人，我们都很幸运
And er...
还有
I, er, in situations like that you think of family a lot.
我，嗯，在那种情况下，一般人都会很想家
I did. Erm...
我也是
And I could look forward to...
我能够有所期盼了
It's become known now that during my tenure
我任期间，了解到
one of our submarines was quite badly damaged.
我们的一艘潜艇毁损非常厉害
I mean, its conning tower was not quite destroyed but very seriously bent.
就是说，它的指挥塔并没有完全毁坏但严重弯曲了
And of course we lied about how it had happened
当然，我们对于事情的原因说了谎
and just said that now it is known it had hit a Soviet submarine
我们只说现在大家都知道是撞上了一艘苏联潜艇
because it was shadowing it.
因为跟得太紧了
Now, boys will be boys
好吧，小伙子就是小伙子
and there was an element of just going off and doing this for bravado
当时似乎就只想着动身出发虚张声势一番
and we needed to curb some of it
我们需要克制一点儿
and I think some of it was curbed.
我想我们也确实被约束了一点儿
The Ministry of Defence has never confirmed any collision with a Soviet submarine.
国防部一直未证实曾与苏联潜艇撞击
Operational details remain classified.
行动细节仍然是机密
On their return home, American, British and Soviet crews
英美苏联船员在回国途中
were forbidden to talk about their patrols.
他们被禁止谈论巡查之事
# No other lips
♪其他人的唇♪
# Could want you more
♪你都不会想要♪
I didn't know very much because he never told me very much.
我不太知道情况因为他没告诉我太多
I knew he was at sea, and I knew he would be gone for three months
我知道他当时在出海，他要去三个月
and they knew that, and that was it, that was it.
他们也知道，就是那样了，就是那样
这些分离的时期是一个考验——充满困难
但再次见到所有人 时感觉棒极了
你能体会到无比的快乐和幸福
孩子们跑来跑去叫着“爸爸回来啦”
他们一直在等爸爸
I was so excited about him coming home, it had been three months,
我很高兴他回家了，都过了三个月了
so I made this big plaque that said "Tonight's the night",
因此我做了这块大饰板，写着“就在今夜”
and I took it down and waved it over the pier.
我带着它走下去在码头上举着挥舞
Well, I was frowned on.
有人冲我皱眉头
Who frowned on you? All the Admirals and their wives.
谁？所有的海军上将和他们的妻子
What did they think was going to happen?
他们觉得会发生什么
I think they thought we were going to have sex.
我想他们觉得我们准备上床
# The wonder of your smile
♪你那笑容的美妙♪
In 1974,
1974年
East and West agreed to reduce their arsenals of nuclear ballistic missiles.
东西方同意减少其核弹道导弹武库
But at sea, western naval intelligence learned of a new threat.
但是在海上，西方海军情报处了解到了新的威胁
The most dangerous ship in the Soviet Fleet,
苏联舰队中最危险的船
a 40,000 ton aircraft carrier called the Kiev.
是一艘叫做基辅的四万吨运载量的航空母舰
Along with fighter aircraft,
配合上歼击机
the Kiev had eight Cruise missiles,
基辅共有八艘巡航导弹
each eight times more powerful
每一颗威力十分
than the bomb that was dropped on Hiroshima.
比投射在广岛的力量强八倍
We were dealing with some pretty big bits of kit.
我们要对付的是一堆大型装备
There was a slight sort of apprehension verging on fear
大家有一点点恐惧
that the Soviet fleet were flexing their muscles.
担心苏联舰队正在展示实力
The carrier was also faster than any submarine.
航母比任何潜艇都要快
Within 18 hours of leaving territorial waters,
在18小时内就能离开领海
she would be capable of launching her missiles on Europe.
它能够对欧洲发射导弹
I name this ship Swiftsure.
我将这艘船命名为敏捷号
May God bless her and all who sail in her.
愿主保佑它和所有船上的人
In early 1977,
1977年初，
Britain's newest hunter killer submarine,
英国最新猎人杀手潜艇
HMS Swiftsure,
皇家海军舰艇敏捷号
was sent north to find the Kiev and record her acoustic signature.
朝北方出发寻找基辅并记录其声音特征
Swiftsure was an operational submarine
敏捷号是一艘行动潜艇
who'd done all its tricks and was ready,
能力俱全，万事俱备
and what's more, about to go on front line deployment.
而且，它将前往前线部署
Oh, it's exciting.
真激动人心
I always found sailing extremely difficult,
我一直觉得航海非常困难
leaving your family knowing that there was going to be
你留下了家人，他们知道
a very significant challenge ahead.
你要面对严峻的挑战
There was a feeling that perhaps in the back of our minds,
我们脑海中大概有这样一种隐约的感觉
Soviets were eight foot tall.
苏联人似乎都八英尺高
We wanted to bring them down to five foot nine,
我们想将他们压倒至五英尺九
which is probably the average.
这样差不多是平均身高
Swiftsure was heading for the Barents Sea,
敏捷号正朝巴伦支海前进，
home to the vast Soviet northern fleet.
巴伦支海是苏联北方广大舰队的老巢
The only way you could detect the potential enemy
监测潜在敌人的唯一方式
was going there close up and covertly.
就是去暗中紧紧跟着，
And when they're operating in their own areas
当他们在自己的海域行动时
they're obviously a little bit freer and easier,
明显更加自由且容易
thinking that maybe they are on their own.
他们觉得是在独处
They were engaged in a very dangerous activity.
他们正进行很危险的活动
But they knew what they were doing, they knew how dangerous it was,
但他们知道自己在做什么，知道有多么危险
they knew how important it was.
也知道多么重要
And they experienced when they did it how difficult it was.
当他们真正做的时候，他们感受到了有多么困难
Among the crew were Russian linguists and electronic intelligence experts.
人员中包括了俄语语言学家和电子情报专家
We were going to do business with the Soviet Navy
我们是在对付苏联海军
so Soviet terms would be used, Russian names would be used.
因此会用到苏联用语，还有俄罗斯人名
Swiftsure would be operating near the Arctic Circle.
敏捷号将在北极圈附近行动
With just an hour of daylight in every 24-hour period,
每24小时只有1小时是白天
special red lighting had to be used.
我们得使用特殊的红光照明
When it's dark up there, which it is for a lot of the time,
当天黑时，也就是大部分时间
light inside, at the bottom of the periscope,
潜望镜底部安装的内部照明灯
has got to be the same or less than the light at the top of the periscope.
亮度需要和潜望镜顶部的灯相等或更暗
It was red lighting for the best part of, probably going to be about two months.
差不多两个月的大部分时间都是红光照明
It became very, very tiring.
非常非常累人
When Swiftsure entered the Barents Sea
当敏捷号进入巴伦支海
the crew found themselves in the middle of a major naval exercise.
船员们发现自己处在一个重大海军演习中
I was surprised at how incredibly busy we really were.
我很惊讶地发现我们有多么忙碌
Your level of activity is absolutely constant, reporting, noise.
你的活跃水平非常稳定,不停地报告声音
I saw missiles streaking through the air.
我看见导弹划破空气
I saw firings by guns.
我看见枪开火
I saw a torpedo firing exercise.
我看见鱼雷开火演习
Never ever in my wildest dreams thought I would do that.
我做梦都想不到自己有一天会做这种事
Well, you're sitting there at the centre of the spider's web.
坐在蜘蛛网中央
It's a lovely feeling of being surrounded by people
这是一种愉快的感觉,你身边都是人
who can't see you but you can see them.
他们看不见你,你却看得见他们
Then, Swiftsure's sonar detected something new.
接着,敏捷号的声呐监听到了新的东西
The Kiev.
基辅
I remember the excitement first time I saw her.
我记得自己第一次看见它时有多兴奋
The captain and the XO had lots sightings before I did
船长和XO在我看见之前已经看了很久
and I remember thinking, come on,
我记得当时在想,拜托
I want to have a look at this. I really want to see her.
我真想看一眼,我想看看它
And when I did she was impressive.
当我真的看到时,觉得她太令人难忘了
Beautiful-looking ship.
真是一艘美丽的船
She was big, clean lines, just looked the part.
她很宏大,流线型,看上去就该是那样的
Soon after that Captain John said, "Right, let's go and have a look at this."
很快约翰船长说:”好了,让我们出发看一看”
We started our approach from behind the carrier,
我们从跟在航母后边开始接近
and obviously we had to go in at a slightly higher speed than his.
很显然我们需要比它的速度稍微快一点儿
We were constantly assessing his course and speed as accurately as we possibly can.
我们不停地分析它的路线和速度,尽可能准确
Coming up from astern you can identify the wash from the propellers.
在船尾上你能够认出螺旋桨卷起的水波
Once we see that we know we are very close.
当看到那个,我们就知道离得很近了
Course 130. Speed 50 knots.
航线130，速度50海里/小时
We needed to match his speed almost exactly.
我们几乎需要完全匹配上它的速度
Going up one revolution at a time.
每次旋转一次
And you give yourself enough time to get down,
你要给自己足够时间下沉
steady on the depth that you want to do this operation at
稳稳停在你想要执行行动的深度
and then slide in underneath.
然后滑下去
It was quite a relief to find that we were sliding under him.
我们很欣慰我们终于滑到它底部了
Gently and without incident, so to speak.
可以说是轻缓而平安无事
Swiftsure's cameras and acoustic devices  .
敏捷号的影像和声音设备
began gathering the Kiev's secrets
开始收集基辅号的秘密
Always tense, always total concentration.
总是充满紧张感，完全集中注意力
How close were you to the Kiev?
当时你们离基辅有多近
Top of the periscope be about 10 to 12 feet.
潜望镜顶部离它大约10至12英尺
We're running 12 feet away from a 40,000 ton aircraft carrier.
我们离这样一艘4万吨载重的航母有12英尺远
Well, so be it. That's what we're doing.
那就这样吧，那就是我们当时做的事情
If that makes you nervous to think about it, yes, fine.
如果这样想让你觉得紧张了，那好吧
But if you're there, you're sharp, you're on the ball.
但如果你当时在那里，你很敏锐，全神贯注
You're not day dreaming while you are doing this, that's for sure.
可以肯定的是你做这一切时并不是在白日做梦
But we are in a little ship.
但我们在一艘小船上
You say it
随你怎么说
but we are in a submarine that could actually sink him in three minutes.
总之我们在一艘能在三分钟内击沉它的潜艇上
He would have difficulty sinking us.
它要击沉我们却不容易
That's the sort of arrogant bit of knowledge to tuck away.
那是我们藏在心里的某种骄傲的认知
We know he's there and we're controlling this whole evolution.
我们知道它在那里，我们掌控着事态发展
And he doesn't know we're there.
它却不知道我们在这里
After we had been underneath for quite a long time
我们在水下呆了较长一段时间以后
we felt we'd seen everything that we could usefully see.
我们觉得自己已经观察到了能看到的一切
We pulled out gently and went off to a decent distance.
我们悄然撤离到了一个安全距离
After 70 days at sea, Swiftsure returned to Britain.
在海上70天后，敏捷号回到了英国
Contained in her sonar bays was the Kiev's entire acoustic fingerprint.
它的声呐储存库中有基辅的所有声音特征
If the carrier ever planned to attack,
如果那艘航母真的计划进攻
the West would be able to find and sink her
西方能够找到并击沉它
before she was in range of Britain or Western Europe.
它没有机会进入英国或西欧范围
It was sharp end, cutting edge of the services.
那是非常尖端的先锋技术
It was the front line of the Cold War operations.
在冷战行动中处于前线
And it was a very exciting thing to be part of.
能成为其一部分是非常激动人心的
Over two decades, British and American hunter killers
二十年来，英国和美国的猎人杀手
brought back vital intelligence about the Soviet fleet.
获得了关于苏联舰队的大量情报
This gave the West a priceless strategic advantage over the Soviet Union.
这使西方比苏联多了极宝贵的战略优势
Well, this was given to me as a parting present by my ship's company
这是所有船员在分别时送给我的
and it says HMS Swiftsure on it.
上面写着皇家海军舰队敏捷号
But this actually is a model made by my ship's company
但实际上这是由全体船员做的一个仿制品
who, over a glass with them, this was presented to me.
一起喝酒的时候，他们把它给了我
I was absolutely delighted.
我开心极了
It's based on the Kiev, the carrier.
这是根据航母基辅的样子做的
Did you talk to your wife about it when you came home? No.
你回家后和妻子聊过这事吗? 没有
I wasn't allowed to do that, no.
我不能这么做，不能
So what did you tell your wife?
那你怎么和你妻子说的？
I said, well, we had a story
我说了我们自己准备的故事
that we had just been on a training patrol.
就是我们进行了一次训练巡逻
That's what all the ship's company were told.
所有船员都是这么被告知的
My wife knew that these were difficult patrols
我妻子只知道巡逻很艰险
and she was used to seeing me come back having lost weight and grown a beard and tense.
她习惯了看到我每次回来都瘦了，长了胡渣而且难以放松
No doubt about that.
这毫无疑问
My wife was absolutely incredible looking after my children.
我妻子在照顾孩子方面真的很伟大
Very, very rarely there.
Through the Swiftsure days through... Tough.
在敏捷号的那些日子，还有其他艰难的日子
The whole part of that world
所有世界另一面的那些正常生活
that you've put to one side for almost two months you pick it up again.
你几乎扔掉了两个月，如今又捡了起来重新生活
You hadn't seen the colour green for a long time.
你很久没有看见绿色了
Grass.
草的颜色
All the delights, you know. The smell of a woman.
还有所有的幸福，你知道的，心爱女人的香味
And I don't mean that salaciously, I just mean smelling a woman.
并不带有色情的成分，我只是说气味
And touch.
和触感
No one touches you in a submarine and that's something that I found I noticed.
我注意到一件事，在潜艇上，没有人碰你
How did it feel?
那回家的感觉怎样？
Ah, it was lovely, lovely.
很愉快，很美妙
What you haven't had you miss.
你思念那些没能拥有的东西
# It's all over
♪一切都结束了♪
# Didn't even cry
♪甚至没有流泪♪
# I just stopped living
♪我只是停止了生活♪
# When you said goodbye
♪在你说再见的时候♪
# It's all over
♪一切都结束了♪
# Didn't feel a thing
♪什么都感觉不到♪
# I just stopped living...
♪我只是不再生活♪
In the next programme, the Russians fight back.
在下一集中，苏联人将要反击
Secret weapons beneath the ice and a disaster at sea.
冰下隐藏的武器以及海上的灾难
http://bbs.3e-online.com   2014.01.10
================================
本字幕僅供學習交流,轉載請注明出處
翻译/校对:scrawl 时间轴/後期:劍齒虎